what is the escape
from pain
most people think most people think it
is
pleasure pleasure to escape from the
pain well they don't necessarily think
that though
i think that's the only escape that they
know so the only attitude that a
so the only attitude that a
person without a right view will have
only one attitude to its pain
which is covered with pleasure
that's the only means of escape that
they know either
trying to get rid of the pain because
that's more pleasant
or to actually finding some different
pleasure to occupy
yourself with so you forget about the
pain either way you turn towards
pleasure in order to avoid pain because you can't
in order to avoid pain because you can't
deal with pain on its own terms
so and that's what the what they said to
say the uh
future doesn't know any other escape
from pain
other than sensuality and sensual
pleasure that's what i was saying before like the
that's what i was saying before like the
um the people are not attracted to
sensuality just because it's pleasant
and gives you that
you know sweet taste or something
they're also dependent on it because
that's the only
means that their mind has of dealing
with pain
so the prospect of sexuality it's
already something people depend on
the possibility of getting places
exactly at least at least
pleasure is is perpetually possible
i might be refraining from it not
engaging with sexuality
but i'm still using the possibility of
pleasure as a relief
from when the pain is there so you still
depend on the pleasure
i can deal with this pain now because
there is
a possibility there is there is a
promise a prospect of pleasure later on
they will be greater so it's worth
enduring this pain now yeah and that's
fine everybody like even when you want
our handshape to be free from suffering you
handshape to be free from suffering you
still have the projected idea of
pleasure through it but the the the whole
through it but the the the whole
practice revolves around actually
not removing your dependence on
sensual pleasure as a mean of dealing
with pain
so removing your dependence even on the
possibility of central pleasure as means
of dealing with pain
that's when people heard heard the
buddha described
nirvana to them the pathogenes in the
sutures they were well they were scared because
they were well they were scared because
in their minds it was like oh that's
basically complete absence of joy
pleasure the only form of joy and pleasure that
the only form of joy and pleasure that
the light in my nose which is central
pleasure so in their minds oh this was like this
so in their minds oh this was like this
is the most depressing miserable
dreadful thing that will kill me and
destroy me if that's
they were they were genuinely genuinely
shocked afraid by it
gripped by anxiety and fear because mind
that depends on pleasure
absence of pleasure means misery
but it doesn't absence and pleasure does
not mean pain
just means absence of pleasure absence
of pain as well
so basically what those people were
afraid of was just a pure neutral
feeling neither pleasant nor unpleasant
neither pleasant nor unpleasant
but the mind that depends on pleasure
neither pleasant means painful
doesn't matter that it's not unpleasant
either the fact that it's not pleasant for the
the fact that it's not pleasant for the
mind that depends on pleasure
is terrifying but it's terrifying not
because in itself it's terrifying it's
terrifying because you're refusing to
give up your dependence on pleasure
out of fear but that fear feeds your
dependence which then makes you afraid which and
which then makes you afraid which and
feeds the defense it's a vicious circle
sensuality or padana or centrality
so this neutral feeling
because of your craving for pleasure
it's it's just exactly and that's what
the suit is say when neutral feeling is
not known not understood not discerned
it will be felt
unpleasantly so that's what i mean like
you you you
nibana is the absence of joy
it's joyless but joylessness does not
mean misery
joylessness means equanimity joylessness
means no joy and no pain means peace means
no joy and no pain means peace means
evenness
but in order to value that the mind
needs to train
to that level needs to train for it
so in other words you need to discern
and develop wisdom
in regard to the neutral feeling and
then it will become the supreme peace of
nibana nothing can match that peace by the mind
nothing can match that peace by the mind
that depends on on pleasure depends on
prospect and
uses at least the possibility of future
pleasure as a means of relief
in regard to the day-to-day pain when
that mind hear joylessness
that is automatically felt as misery
absolute depressing overwhelming pain it's not
depressing overwhelming pain it's not
pleasant
but it's not unpleasant either but you
don't get to value the fact that it's
not unpleasant either
because you're too concerned about there
is no joy
so that's the sense restraint needs to
be done before
if you have through sense restraint you
basically start training yourself
towards joylessness of sensuality
joylessness of sensuality
and then again the root of sensuality as
the would have said so many times is
your delight in the joy that you get on
delight in the joy that you get on
account of it it's not the beautiful or
tasty objects in the world
so the root of sensuality is your
dependence on that type of pleasure
nothing else remove that dependence on
that pleasure and you will find peace
so sense restraint is physically
preparing you
withdrawing you from that pleasure so
that mentally you can see
how gratuitously you depend on it and
then choose to withdraw yourself because
ah
this is not worth clinging to as the
certain would say
but if you're not physically withdrawn
you will never mentally
be able to like um stop depending on it
so sense restraint means basically
emulating nibana
pretty much emulating the non-dependence
on on joy that's
that's acquired through senses
but you need to start doing it even if
you still want
to have it mentally physically at least
you need to do it wrong
verbally you need to be withdrawn and
then eventually mentally
you'll be able to do so as well but yeah
once you start withdrawing yourself from
that engaging in pleasures then
engaging in pleasures then
what will naturally occur is that
experience of mutual freedom well
exactly once you start with withdrawing yourself
once you start with withdrawing yourself
physically from pleasures
that's already training for you to be
able to endure the neutral feeling and
not freak out in regard to it
so only people that are not withdrawn
bodily verbally mentally from sensuality
lose their mind when they recognize what
nibana is or that will kill me that will
destroy me
if you already have been cultivating
sense restraint
say no to yourself taming your senses
practicing sense control
it's not going to be as frightening the
joylessness of nibana will be something you can
of nibana will be something you can
actually get closer to
as opposed to lose your mind fall on the
ground pull your hair beat the breasts
in despair like oh that will kill me as
they did
when the buddha would clearly show over
nibbana what his teaching is
and that's what it's always said like
like those who are
free from passion they have no like
fear even in face of death because
that's what that is cessation of these
senses upon which
well upon which pleasures i depend
but those who are free from passion even
when these senses are threatened
there is no fear because there is no
passion i there's no dependence on the
pleasure of the senses
so the absence of passion
means no fear of death means no fear of
nibana means no fear of this passion doesn't
means no fear of this passion doesn't
mean it means peace depression
doesn't mean exactly depression it's
only generated
from the point of view you still depends
on the pleasure and now you found
something that fully like crushes that dependence
that fully like crushes that dependence
removes it and there is no more future
of it
and that is scary because you refuse to
give it up because neutral feeling in
itself is scary
so it's joyless but it's also
there is but that all that doesn't mean
it's miserable
so absence of joy and absence of misery
that's a absence of ambitious and like a
thirsty inspiration for achievement
and absence of depression as the
arahants in the suit
would say in the terra terra terrigata i
delight not in life
there's absolutely no delight towards
anything in this life
through the senses and i delight not in
death either
i await my time that's it and that's the
arahants declaration
there's no delight and a description of
the fourth genre that's the
you know perfect complete surmounting
yeah equanimity
you know uh upeka sati is
but it's yes amounting of that pleasure
and pain and
joy and grief and disappearance of that
pleasure and pain it's it's completely steady
and pain it's it's completely steady
mind
in the neutral feeling that's the whole
point
and that's what the ghana is even the
first jhana it's it's already
from the point of view of non-ghana
first genre it's like steadying your
mind in a neutral feeling
neutral from that point of view
obviously you can go even further
and and refine that neutral feeling up
to the point of john equanimity
but even the first genre starts by
abandoning joy and grief in regard to
the world
and unification of the mind that comes
on a kind of thinking and pondering and
so on
and that in itself it's felt pleasantly
in a sense of a neutral peace
neutral feeling when understood it's
felt pleasantly that's what they said to
say neutral feeling when not understood it
neutral feeling when not understood it
is felt unpleasant
so it's the understanding your knowledge
your discernment of it
determines how you're going to feel it
so
joylessness when understood it's
pleasant because there's no disturbance
because there's no disturbance
joylessness when not understood
it's miserable dreadful anxious
overwhelming so how do you prepare yourself to endure
so how do you prepare yourself to endure
it that which is overwhelmingly
anxious and so on by starting the sense
restraint by seeing the danger in the slightest
by seeing the danger in the slightest
fault by being watchful
mindful careful you're already
practicing strength
to be able to endure the neutral feeling
which is initially going to try to scare
you and then you train yourself for that and
and then you train yourself for that and
this passion is being developed
again it comes back to also the other
talk we did on non-activity
non-engagement fear of boredom that
people have nothing to do so
whether they practice buddhism or not
everything just becomes another thing i
do to keep myself
occupied because otherwise i get
overwhelmed by the neutrality
i mean boredom is truly just neutral yet
it's the most dreadful thing for every
mind that's not developed
so the more understanding you're gaining
the more pleasurable becomes that
neutral feeling
that absence of joy
it's not that you know arahan's feelings
is so like a mystical dimension no it's
just three types of feeling whether
you're protruding or another hunter
it's just how much influence those three
types of feeling
have over you and your decisions and
your views and your assumptions
or whether you're free from views and
assumptions in regard to these feelings
and then in the felt there's just the
felt in the scene is just to see her just to
in the scene is just to see her just to
her
same principle so the feeling that's
felt you're neutral in regard to it
there's no pressure so there's no
pressure it means truly there's really
no feeling there anymore
in that sense ketogenic feeling are gone
in another hand but it doesn't mean that
has no uh aggregate of feeling anymore
so how can arahan feel without feeling
seeming contradiction well
develop understanding of a neutral
feeling and you'll see
and that's the same like when sauriputta
declared oh what a pleasure what a
pleasure and then dying i think in the suit has
and then dying i think in the suit has
asked him
what you mean what's the pleasure says
nibana it's it's pleasure it's like but
didn't you on another occasion saying
ibana there is nothing felt
and he says yes and that's what is
pleasant the fact is nothing felt
it's pleasant so the understanding of
there's no feeling here
it's very agreeable
and it's it all boils down to
development in regard to the neutral
feeling obviously in order for to begin even any
obviously in order for to begin even any
development in regard to neutral feeling
and being able to endure it and
withstand it
you need to stop habitually giving into
the pleasant feeling
and feeding the thirst for more pleasure
and you have to habitually
stop giving in to the um feeling of the
unpleasant feeling
trying to get rid of it resisting it
you are by doing these two things you
are equipping yourself
to endure neutrality that's felt neither
pleasantly but not unpleasantly either
clarifying it exactly by enduring it you
as i said you're becoming more familiar
with it so
non-activity uh enduring the initial
anxiety of boredom
and finding value in it and even that's
what we would say like the solitude
is for somebody who has developed wisdom
to start finding pleasure in solitude
otherwise you won't
otherwise it's terrifying
without wisdom solitude mind cannot bear
it and
again the buddha did outline what you
need to prepare beforehand
so that you can benefit from solitude
which is
impeccable virtue seeing the danger in
the slightest fault
um sure janas but you know they usually
come with solitude
sense restraint right view all these
things you develop beforehand and then
if you go to forest
remote dwellings where there's only wild
animals living and so on
you your mind will not overwhelm you you
will be benefiting from it the
neutrality of it well
if you're in a position where there's
nothing to do basically exactly
you don't need to be top of the forest
yeah top like a remote forest
or an empty hut yeah empty of activity
empty effectivity empty of distraction
empty of others turning as they please
so
physically removed but yes apartment
will do just fine
you do want to have the environment that
will support that but again don't think
that that will do the work for you
you will be ready for the solitude if
you've already practiced sensitive
strength in regards to the world
if you have already endured joys and
griefs in regard to the world without
acting out of it habitually
that's how you surmount it not by
running into the solitude or hiding in
the forest
because sometimes yeah people try to
contrast yes see the buddha said we
should go to the remote dwellings and so
on because they don't want to deal with
their own sense restraint and stuff here
no that's like the second group of herd
dear heard from that sutter that we did
also recently
that shan's debate and runs a double
mountain but there's no wisdom
development so sense restraint in regard to the
so sense restraint in regard to the
world in regard to the central polls in
regards to dependence on the joys and so
on
needs to be developed and needs to be
endured it's going to be painful
because not because of the sensory
strain but because of your dependence
on joys of sensuality that's why you
suffer when you first restrain yourself
you don't suffer because you say no to
yourself you suffer because
you've been saying yes to yeah you can't
change yes all this time
so say no to yourself just reveals your
addiction your dependence
on these gratuitous sensual joys
that you're responsible yeah did you
fully feeding maintaining
yeah adding to proliferating
so practice towards joylessness
when joylessness is understood it's the
utmost peace
agreeability it's nibana because now joy
means joylessness means no delight would
you like me
and it also means no misery and being
unable to be miserable
or scared or affected by any type of
pain on a kind of anything
including impending death dying you know
terminal diagnosis or whatever else
which eventually will have to occur
no more prospect of pleasure well things
that are
being will be destroyed by death
are not things you depend on anymore why
because you removed your dependence on
gratuitous joy that came out of them
you removed your delight so joylessness
that will die before you die
become joyless and you will be unable to
be miserable as well